<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most breefe, easie and plaine receite for faire writing Wherin the author being well acquainted with the causes, which in these daies hinders it, hath for the good of his cuntrie, so distinguished and broken euery perticular letter for the true making thereof, and so perfectly and plainely shewed the ready way of true ioyning the same. Both for the roman and secretary handes, as any one of ordinarye yeres and capacity, not hindring any other busines, may at his idle times by his own priuate practise, in short time attaine to write, to serue very good vses either in office or otherwise.</title>
            <author>Panke, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19172.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110196</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845790</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845790</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10711</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10711)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 382:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most breefe, easie and plaine receite for faire writing Wherin the author being well acquainted with the causes, which in these daies hinders it, hath for the good of his cuntrie, so distinguished and broken euery perticular letter for the true making thereof, and so perfectly and plainely shewed the ready way of true ioyning the same. Both for the roman and secretary handes, as any one of ordinarye yeres and capacity, not hindring any other busines, may at his idle times by his own priuate practise, in short time attaine to write, to serue very good vses either in office or otherwise.</title>
                  <author>Panke, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[dward] A[llde] for Iohn Perin, and are to be solde in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Angell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1591]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed and dated: Vltimo Septembris. 1591. W. Panke.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>With spaces left for examples to be added by hand (filled in in only copy known).</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19172+ on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penmanship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:1"/>
            <p>A Moſt breefe, eaſie and plaine receite for faire writing.</p>
            <p>Wherin the Author being well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the cauſes, which in theſe daies hinders it, hath for the good of his Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, ſo diſtinguiſhed and broken euery perticular letter for the true making thereof, and ſo perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainely ſhewed the ready way of true ioyning the ſame.</p>
            <p>Both for the Roman and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary handes, as any one of ordinarye yeres and capacity, not hindring any other bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, may at his idle times by his own priuate prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, in ſhort time attaine to write, to ſerue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good vſes either in office or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by E. A. for Iohn Perin, and are to be ſolde in Paules Churchyard at the ſigne of the Angell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull my <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler good Maiſter, M. Thomas Powle Eſquire, one of the ſixe Clarkes of her</hi> Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt honourable Courte of Chauncery. <hi>W. P.</hi> wiſheth all happines with increaſe of ſpirituall bleſsinges in the greateſt meaſure.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull I haue here vndertaken a woorke, how profitable, I referre to the euent. And for that I had no better meanes then this to manifeſt my duetie I haue preſumed to make your W. the patrone of my trauell: wherein if you ſhalbe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to allow me your ordinarie fauour, it will be of force ſufficient not onelye to defend me from the greateſt aduerſarie, but alſo to arme and encourage me to a worke of better effect. Thus as I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to commit vnto your W. this my firſt croppe, ſo will I in my beſt exerciſes commend all your actions to be gouerned by the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your W. moſt bounden ſeruant in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of his duetie. W. Pank.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, in reſpect that many would willinglye attayne the perfection of writing, and cannot, either for that their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding is too farre off, or helde backe by occaſion of buſines or otherwiſe (which is moſt like,<note place="margin">Such as teach by great.</note>) that ſome newlye ſprong in that knowledge, haue rated it ſo high as the greater ſort that would, cannot, by reaſon of the price, and other better able for the ſame cauſe will not. This Author hath deuiſed ſuch plain, eaſie, &amp; exact, rules for faire writing,<note place="margin">Though they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hand<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led pen.</note> as any one of ordinary yeeres and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, (much more they of greater iudgement) not ſubiect to impediment, may in a ſhort ſpace, at idle times not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring their other buſines, and by their owne priuate prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice attain, to write both the ſecretary, and roman hand, to ſerue very good vſes either in office or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>And to the end, that he would auoide all occaſions that might hinder his honeſt meaning in this his profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble woorke: he promiſeth to ſuch as ſhall buye his booke, that whatſoeuer either in the ſame, or otherwiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to writing ſhall ſeeme hard, that he will gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſhew it them by woord of mouth, if they repaire vnto him. <hi>Vltimo Septembris. 1591.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Quod ignoras, ne doceas.</hi> W. Panke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Firſt I haue thought good to begin with the breaking of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perticular letter.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="a"/> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> the plaineſt and eaſieſt waye is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you make the firſt parte round thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> (for to make it otherwiſe will ſeeme hard to a learner) then, from the vttermoſt parte therof, towards your right hand, make a ſmall ſtroke thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which doone, ſet on your pen where you faſtned your laſt ſtroak, and from thence draw down a ſtraight ſtroake no lower then your firſte compaſſe thus. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="b"/> your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is thus made. Firſt make a ſlope ſtroak thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> at the vpper end wherof ſet your pen, and turning it ouer a little towardes your lefte hand thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> bring it ſtraight downe ſo far as your lyne that you writ vpon thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which doone, ſet your pen a little behinde the end therof thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it ſtraight forward thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then turne it vp round in this manner <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="c"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is eaſily made with a ſtraight ſtroake thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which done, ſet your pen on the toppe of it, and with the edge as ſmall as you can drawe a ſtroke from your right hand forward, halfe ſo long as your firſt ſtraight ſtroke thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="d"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is made with the halfe of the firſt parte of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which done, make a ſtraight ſlope
<pb facs="tcp:10711:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſtroake ioyning to the higheſt parte of your former compaſſe thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and ſo at once cloſe him round, ſo as it may ſtill kéep his compaſſe as an <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="e"/> For your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> make your firſt parte of the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which done, ioyne to the head of it another like compaſſe, halfe as big as the firſt thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="f"/> For your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> the plaineſt and eaſieſt way for a learner, is to make it as you made the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and then ſtrike the ſame ſtroake ſomewhat longer thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="g"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is made with the firſt ſtroke of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> turned round at the foot iuſt as high as the firſt ſtroak thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which done, ſet your pen where you laſt tooke it off, and drawing it downe as lowe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is long thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> turn it quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the edge of your pen towardes your lefte hand thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and cloſe it at the head in the ſame manner and with the ſame ſtroake as you made your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="h"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is made with the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which done, ſet your pen in the loweſt part of it, and with the edge of your pen make a very ſmall ſtroke, and carrie it ſlope a little way thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which done, turne it round thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and in the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it from the end of the compaſſe, drawe a ſlope ſtroke towards your left hand néere the length of the body thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then ſet your pen at the end therof and turne it vp round lightlye towardes the bellye with a reaſonable compaſſe thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is eaſily made, for it is ſimply the firſte parte of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> or the laſt ſtroke of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="k"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is made with the firſt parte of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> with the ſame foot that your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is before it is turnde round thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then make a ſmall compas which is the eye, as neere the middeſt as you can thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and in the middeſt iuſt between the eye and the foote make a ſtroke through thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="l"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is likewiſe eaſily made, for it is onelye the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="m"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is made with the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then ſet your pen at the foote of the ſame ſtroke and carrie vp your hand a ſlope from the foot to the head with the edge of your pen thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the toppe of the ſame ſtroke bring downe ſuch another ſtroke as your firſte and no lower, thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then from the foote of the ſecond ſtraight ſtroake, carrie vp another ſlope ſtroake as you did before: and ſo from the head of that ſlope ſtroake bring downe a third ſtraight ſtroake thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is made.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="n"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> I néed not ſtand vpon, for it is the two firſt ſtraight ſtrokes of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="o"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is ſimple the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="p"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is made with the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ſauing that it muſt be ſomewhat ſlope towardes the right hand, and turning backe a very little to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the lefte hand thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then at the foote therof and a little behinde it ſet your pen and make the ſame compaſſe as you did to the belly of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then ſetting your pen where you tooke it of laſt and make a ſtraight ſtroke as low as the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is long, thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="q"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is ſimplie your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ſauing that you muſt bring down the firſt ſtroke of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> as far below the proportion of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> as your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is long, thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="r"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is eaſily made alſo, for if you mark it it is but the firſte parte of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your pen iuſt in the middeſt of the loweſt flat ſtroke thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> carry vp your hand directlye as high and no higher then your firſt ſtroke, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all with the edge of your pen at the top of the ſame ſtroke, ſtrike the like ſmall ſtroke as you did to the head of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ſ"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which we call the long <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is beſt made as you make your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> (till you be more perfect) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that the loweſt parte of the head muſt be ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what further off from the body of it thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="s"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which we call the round or little <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is eaſieſt made with your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> at the higheſt part wherof toward your right hand ſet your pen and drawe a little ſlope ſtroake thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which turned backeward a verye little towardes the lefte hand makes your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="t"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is a ſtraight full ſtroake, ſauing that the toppe of it is ſomewhat ſlope thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and the ſtroke thorough the ſame muſt you make no néerer nor higher from the foot of it then that between the ſame ſtroke and the foot you may eaſily make an <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="v"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is alredy ſhewed you, for it is the firſt whole parte of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="w"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is likewiſe your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ſauing that the laſt part is your ſingle <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> or the head of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="x"/> Your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is made with a ſlope ſtroke thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp round from the foot to the head thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> then ſetting your pen where you laſt took it off, compaſſe it round to your right hand thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="y"/> your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> is very eaſie, for it is but the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> with the taile of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ioyned to it thus. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>NOw that I haue ſhewed you the breaking and making of euery perticular letter in the croſſe rowe, it is as neceſſary to ſhewe you how to ioyne and ſet them in their order.</head>
               <p>Firſte you muſt ſpeciallye marke how many of your letters haue whites or compaſſes.</p>
               <p>And euery one of them in wordes as they fall out, muſt you as néere as you can make of like bignes, as for example <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and your blackes which is al the ſtrokes in euery letter alſo: muſt be of like fulnes as néere as you can: yet for your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> it is tollerable that you make them fuller then the reſt.</p>
               <p>All the letters in the croſſe row excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> are to be ioyned to the foote of them thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>There is no other letters to be ioyned but theſe that follow, and they muſt be ioyned thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> all the reſt muſt ſtand as cloſe as they that ioyne, as thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. ſauing the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> which you may ioyne thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>Muſt you ioyne all your letters alike as <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and as you thus ioyne your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> to
<pb facs="tcp:10711:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
euery of theſe perticular letters, ſo muſt you doo alſo all your other letters, excepting <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> which you may cloſely ſet by thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>All your letters muſt ſtand cloſe <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> not ioyning to the belly, as <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. I ſet no more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for that theſe letters are in effect the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to all the reſt of the letters in the croſſe row.</p>
               <p>It is ſufficient that you ſet the vſuall letters that followes it in this manner <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> for you ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue any other letter follow <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> beſides <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>You muſt ſet euery letter that followes it, as néere to the bodye of it, as the reſt of your letters ſtand one from another thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> you muſt ſet all the letters thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>FOr the ſetting of your woordes, the diſtance of them is vſuallye knowne: viz. betwéene euerye woord the ſpace of an <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and as you keepe equall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betwéene your woordes, the like care muſt you haue for your letters, that they ſtand not one wider or cloſer, or one higher or lower then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>For the Roman hand.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Diſtinguiſhing of Letters.</head>
               <p>TO learne to make your letters ſpéedily.</p>
               <p>Firſt eſpeciallye marke how many letters are made after one faſhion, by noting whereof you ſhall very eaſilye attaine to the making of al your letters, as for example. Make the halfe of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe ſomewhat longer then your ſecretary <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> which makes the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>The next is a ſlope ſtroke towardes your left hand thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> which is the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you ſhall make your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>The next is this little ſtroke ſomewhat ſlope, and a little longer then your ſecretary <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> which is a letter of it ſelfe called <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> whereby you make <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and by drawing it ſomewhat longer thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> makes your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> with the firſt ſtroke of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> turned backward thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>The little <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> hauing their proportion of themſelues. I will ſhew how to make them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward in the true making of letters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now that I haue thus diſtinguiſhed euery letter, I will likewiſe ſhew you how euery letter is made by himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10711:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The making of the Letters.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="a"/> THe <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is made with his firſt compas as before thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> which done, ſet your pen on the higheſt parte thereof where you firſte began it, and from thence draw downe a ſtroke like vnto your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> as lowe and no lower then your firſt compas thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="b"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is made with the firſte ſtroke as before thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> which done, ſet your pen iuſt aboue the foot as high as you meane to make the reſt of your let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in deapth thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and ſo carrying it round as I ſhewed you in the head of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> cloſe him iuſt in the foot as round as you can thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="c"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is ſimplie your firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ſauing that at the head you muſt make it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what full thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="d"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is alſo your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and till you grow ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what perfect, when you ſhould make a <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> make an <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and then to the higheſt corner ioyne cleanly the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="e"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is alſo your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> turned in a little at the head thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is alſo the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> being iuſt in the middeſt turned backward like the foote of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="g"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is alſo your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> being brought downe a little way with a ſlope ſtroke thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> then carrye your pen with a ſmall ſtroke ſomewhat compaſſe toward your left hand thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and from thence car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him with another ſlope ſtroake back towardes
<pb facs="tcp:10711:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
your right hand and vp to the head of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="h"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is made as your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ſauing that you muſt leaue it open onely at the foot thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is made before <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="k"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is made with the firſt ſtroke of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> then as high from the foote of the ſtroke as the top of the bellye of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> make a little eye thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> at the loweſt end whereof ſet your pen and make a ſlope ſtroke no lower then the foote of the firſt ſtroke thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="l"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is onely the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="m"/> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="n"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is thus made, firſt with your then from the middeſt thereof make a ſmall ſlope ſtroke with the edge of your pen as high &amp; no high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then your firſt ſtroke thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> that done, ſet your pen at the top of that laſt ſmall ſtroke and make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother little ſtroke as your firſt no lower then the ſame, nor wider nor cloſer at head then at foot thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and ſo for the third ſtroke doo in all reſpectes as you did for the ſecond thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="o"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is eaſily made for it is but the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> turned round to the head thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="p"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is onely the latter halfe of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> with the belly of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="q"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is onlye your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ſauing that your muſt make the laſt part of it ſomewhat longer thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="r"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is onely the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="s"/> The little <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> hath his proportion of himſelfe and the eaſieſt way for a learner is to make a litle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe thus ſmall <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and ſo to make the like backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:10711:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ioyning to the bottom of the firſt thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="t"/> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is ſimplie your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ſauing that it muſt be a little longer vpward thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="u"/> The ſingle <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is but two ſtrokes like your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ioyned together at the foote, and one no higher nor lower then another nor wider at head then at foote thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="v"/> This <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is alſo a ſingle <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and it is thus made. Firſt make ſuch a ſtroke as this <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> then ſet your pen at the ende thereof, and with the edge of your pen make a ſlope ſtroke vp towards your left hand thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and ſo at once carry it compaſſe vp as high and no higher then your firſt ſtroke thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is onely two of thoſe compaſſes ioyned together thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> is made with the head of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and the firſt part of your <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ioyned together <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="x"/> TOuching the ioyning of this hand, I take it, that there is no neceſſitie therein, for it is moſt vſually written vnioyned &amp; commendable. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my opinion when you haue attained the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection of the letter, if you will obſerue but a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable diſtance in the ſetting of your letters &amp; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in your words you ſhal finde it more eaſie and beſt. For ioyning of the letters wilbe (in a learner) a cauſe of cloſe writing, which in a Roman hand is not tollerable.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10711:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
